<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chris Wright&#39;s Election Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chris Wright&#39;s Election Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 4: Incumbency</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/30/week-4-incumbency/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/30/week-4-incumbency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;incumbency-advantage&#34;&gt;Incumbency Advantage&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/30/week-4-incumbency/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/30/week-4-incumbency/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-the-incumbent&#34;&gt;Who is the incumbent?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-for-a-change-model&#34;&gt;Time for a change model&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/30/week-4-incumbency/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/20/polling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/20/polling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;gallup.jpg&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; height=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The picture above is of George Gallup. Gallup is considered to be the father of public opinion polling and founded the namesake polling organization, Gallup. Since Gallup revolutionized polling, it has been a mainstay when talking about elections. Although polls are widely conducted and a focal point of campaign news, the validity and accuracy of polls has always been in question. In the 1948 election, polls famously predicted a Dewey victory over Truman and more recently some polls underestimated the support for Trump in the 2016 election. These polling mishaps lead to one essential question: What makes a good poll?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamentals I: Economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/14/fundamentals-i-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/14/fundamentals-i-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Read my lips: no new taxes&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;ndash; George H. W. Bush.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Despite making this promise, Bush later reversed course on the statement and raised taxes. This decision by George H.W. Bush at the 1988 Republican National Convention is often cited as one of the reasons why he lost reelection in 1992. Other one-term presidents like Herbert Hoover and Jimmy Carter have seen their reelection chances dwindle based on their economic policy and the overall economic performance in the United States. This week, I will further examine the connection between economic performance and an incumbent&amp;rsquo;s reelection chance. To achieve this, I will complete extension 1 by creating several predictive models based on key economic indicators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 1: Electoral Competitiveness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/09/week-1-electoral-competitiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/09/09/week-1-electoral-competitiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my blog for GOV 1347. Throughout the semester I will be updating this blog and examining various techniques to forecast the 2024 election. For the first week the focus is electoral competitiveness. This blog will analyze the competitiveness of presidential elections and analyze which state vote Democrat or Republican consistently&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;electoral-competitveness&#34;&gt;Electoral Competitveness&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To examine whether elections in the US are competitive I utililzed a dataset of the presidential popular vote since 1948. Using this data, I plotted the popular vote for the Democrats and Republicans over time. If elections were competitive, you would expect to see lines that are close to one another and a back-and-forth trend in the winner of the popular vote.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
